hello and welcome everyone to the active
inference lab
today it is january 10 2022
and we're here in active guest stream
number 14 with a whole host of awesome
guests
we're going to be discussing osteopathy
and mental health
and we're going to have the authors say
hello and introduce themselves then
lucas will give a presentation and
during the presentation please feel free
to add your comments in questions in the
live chat and then we'll have a bunch of
time after the presentation to ask those
questions to the authors hear any
author's remarks so
really excited to hear from you all and
learn from your perspective
let's hear the introductions from the
authors and then go to lucas so please
robert and then we'll kick it off from
there thank you
uh yeah robert shaw i'm based in sweden
i'm an osteopath and a psychotherapist
my research interest is particularly
with embodiment
and that was what my phd was on
embodiment within the therapeutic
relationship
hi everyone i'm francesco
italy
from italy uh i'm a neuroscientist and
an ostropop
uh mainly um
interest in uh discovering the uh how
the brain
works uh in relation to touch in
relation to the
effect of touch
based on the different
type of
stimuli
that the the body received
hi uh i'm george ester jestervilles i'm
an osteopath i'm currently based in
malta and italy
i'm also a cognitive scientist and my
main interest is on predictive
processing active entrance touch and
chronic pain in general
yeah hi my name is uh lucas i think i'm
the last of the authors so i'm an
osteopath as well based in hamburg in
germany and i'm
currently working part-time at the
osteopathic research institute
and i'm working there in education
education and research and i'm also
part-time studying psychology and
neuroscience at mentor augmented health
at king's college in london
and i think i can kick off the
presentation now that's okay with you
tanya
perfect thanks
so
um yeah we have uh the opportunity
thanks again for the active appearance
lab for the invitation it's it's a
pleasure to be here
we have the opportunity to present a
paper that we have recently published in
frontiers in psychology in the section
health psychology
the research topic
called an activism and active appearance
in the therapeutic alliance
and the paper is entitled osteopathy and
mental health and embodied predictive
and introspective framework
and um yeah without further ado i think
let's let's dive right into it
um a little introduction on on why these
things might be interesting
um
we have a
globally a very high prevalence and a
burden but also comorbidity between
musculoskeletal
and uh mental health disorders so to put
this in perspective about uh one billion
prevalent cases of mental disorders have
been reported in
2017 while about 1.3 billion prevalent
cases have been reported of
musculoskeletal disorders in 2017. so
together these uh two broad spectrum of
disorders are um very prevalent but also
burdensome so
together both both conditions contribute
um to
other main contributors to to work by
disability
but um musculoskeletal mental disorders
also highly co-morbid which means for
example that anxiety depression are
frequently core core with chronic and
often musculoskeletal pain conditions
and vice versa
so
for example depressive symptoms are
quite prevalent and
pain suffers and pain symptoms are also
quite prevalent in individuals with
depression
um so
these uh this data kind of outlines in a
need to to integrate physical and mental
health care services in our opinion but
also in the opinion of
many research papers in the literature
so um especially multidisciplinary
collaborations between most skeleton and
psychological healthcare specialists
have been called for
but on the other hand there have also
been some disease classifications that
have been proposed to to combine
physical and mental health
um
and propose classifications that are
neither purely somatic nor julian mental
so
we believe that there is this need to
integrate these kind of
approaches
and we like to propose osteopathy to be
to be one of these approaches
and
osteopathy for those who don't know is
generally used primarily to treat
musculoskeletal disorders like back pain
but
um it is also
uh has recently been proposed to benefit
psychosocial factors in particular in
in patient populations with persistent
pain
and
there have also there was also some
research that has been conducted from
hillary abbey and colleagues showing
some positive outcomes
of combined treatment as a
combined osteopathy and combined
psychological informed strategies
uh showing positive results
so there are only a few attempts to to
investigate the effectiveness of
osteopathy in the field of mental health
and there are only a few approaches
being developed
to treat or to engage with mental health
so
based on this background we proposed um
we tried to propose a framework on how
to move forward and how to research the
putative effects of osteopathy in this
field
and we do so by drawing together um
from the research fields of embodied
cognition predictive coding but also
interception and osteopathy
and we like to propose in the end our
framework which is an embodied
predictive and introspective remote
and if you look on the right hand side
figure one this is kind of our
background put together and to simplify
body cognition kind of highlights the
role of the body and cognition and the
mental health
and these process processes are likely
underpinned by predictive coding
processes
so
furthermore our access point
we discuss interception as an access
point and therapeutic access point to to
affect these processes and we argue that
osteopathy might might be an approach to
to realize this aim
so let's have a look at the
background we start with the first
research field which is
embodied cognition
and
generally embodied embodiment is an
interdisciplinary field of research
which spans disciplines
including philosophy but also psychology
psychiatry and neuroscience
and in general these theories of
embodiment argue that the cognition and
emotion are both dependent on embedded
embodied simulations
so
they argue that body and mind are
inseparable in producing cognition and
that the non-neural body
might both constrain and enable
cognition
but notably there are stronger and
weaker versions of embodiment
some argue that the body might
contribute to
cognitive processes while
other
versions argue that it might constitute
cognitive processes
so to
get a little bit more detail involved
theories of embodiment argue that
cognition and emotion are based upon
reinstatements of perception so this is
relating to both external extra
receptive and inter meaning interceptive
sensory states
but also to action which relates to
proprioceptive motor states
and these perceptions produce
embodied or sensory motor simulations
which of previous experiences in one's
self so this is a
kind of explanation of embodiment
and
this perspective is quite interesting
because it might revise our
brain-centered view of cognition by
acknowledging that these processes are
not simply limited to neural events in
the brain but also cut across the brain
body and world divisions and should be
also studied accordingly
and there are different kinds of
commitment to the embodied
theories
and and activism is an interesting
aspect or linked concept that i want to
to go into detail a little bit further
and an activism proposes that cognition
emerges from the dynamic interaction of
brain body and also environment so um
most of you might have heard about the
4e cognition um which is
that cognition is all together embodied
embedded and acted extended but also
ecological
and um we are or at this argument that
cognition is an
embodied embedded enacted extended and
ecological
process
of sense making
through a body in an environment so this
is an evaluate evaluative interaction of
an organism and its environment
so in detail these four or five e's mean
that
body cognition is enabled through and
also constrained by the non-neural body
embedded means that cognition depends on
the environmental context
as the organism is situated within the
environment
and enacted means that cognition is for
action and depends on the interaction of
the embodied organism with the
environment
and extended means that cognition
extends beyond the brain and body into
the environment the most notable example
might be your smartphone
and lastly ecological means that
cognition depends on the environmental
affordances for for action
and all together this might
constitute
an activism
with a 5e perspective
so combining these perspectives
of embodied and active
inactivism
both mental and physical health
conditions for example pain and
depression
um are associated with alterate
interaction with an altered interaction
of the organism within with with the
environment through its embodiment
so it's the three-part interaction of
brain body and environment
so to sum this up embodiment and
activism emphasized the interaction of
brain body and environment in
understanding the mind and cognition
and
to understand the the processes of the
brain in a little bit more detail we
have to turn to another field of
research which is the next part of the
background this is predictive coding
and i believe that predictive coding is
a
topic most of the listeners are more
familiar with than us but i try to
summarize them anyway
so predictive processing
is a theoretical framework with growing
influence in the field of cognitive
science
and it is
closely related but also distant uh
distinct from the free energy principle
asian brain hypothesis and active
inference so i will summarize all of
them closely
shortly
so
the free energy principle proposes that
living systems resist the tendency to
disorder or another words
remain in thermodynamic non-equilibrium
steady states
and they do so by restricting themselves
to a limited number of states
through the minimization of free energy
and in in this instance free energy is
defined as the difference between a
system's predicted and actual states
and this can be minimized using both
perception and action
and perception it is minimized by
updating the prediction
that is made from the generated model
based on the sensation
and action in turn
is changing the sensation through action
to match with the prediction so it's
like a self-fulfilling prophecy
and the bayesian brain hypothesis
proposes that brains make predictions
about the causes of extra receptive
interceptive but also proprioceptive
sensations
um using both the current sensory input
but also prior beliefs based on the
generated model
and in general
the confidence or precision one has
uh in the belief or the prior
um
and the sensory input or the likelihood
will determine how much the perception
will in the end shift towards the
expectation
so
um
in general a gap between prior and
likelihood is called a prediction error
or free energy
and
while a system is minimizing prediction
error or free energy or surprise or
entropy that is also maximizing the
evidence for its own model of the world
and this is the bargaining brain
hypothesis is relating to behavior so
predictive coding is putting this into a
neural perspective and proposes that
there are descending top-down
predictions that are
conveyed from higher cortical levels
down to lower cortical levels
where they are compared to
us and bottom-up sensory information
so
from this perspective information only
goes up the cortical hierarchy and if a
mismatch between the predicted and
actual information occurs which is terms
of prediction error
and otherwise top-down predictions
constantly explain away
bottom sensory information
so
then there's active imperance which
proposes that the brain
actively modifies its input to confirm
prior expectations
and this is an inactive and also
selective sampling of sensory
information in the world through action
so
prediction errors can be minimized we've
talked about it a little bit through
perceptual influence and active
endurance uh perceptive appearance
meaning revising the generated model
based on the prediction errors and
active inference
acting on the world to to generate a
state that is predicted by the
generative one
and to bring all of this together within
the physical mental health condition
to understand the physical and mental
health conditions
it might be an altered weighting of
prior beliefs and sensory information
which gives rise to physical mental
health conditions
so for example physical health
conditions
prior beliefs are likely overweighted
relative to sensory information which
means i follow too much prediction uh
precision
which then predicts symptoms
consequently experienced
and
this might also lead to heightened
prediction of pain even towards harmless
sensations so that harmless sensations
might be perceived as painful
and on the other hand mental health
conditions
um both
prior beliefs might be overly precise
compare in comparison to sensory
information or vice versa
and so the first one is depression and
the second one in psychosis
and
yes
so
one point that was quite
interesting is that chronic pain and
depression which we are quite interested
in are particularly linked to false
experiences of interception there's a
little literature about this so that's
this is our next research topic that we
want to uh to combine with the other
ones
um so what is interception
um kaiser and i
have defined interception as
the process by which the nervous system
senses
interprets and integrates signals
originating from within the body so it's
all information from within our own body
and this provides uh some kind of
embodied sensory experience
um which is absolutely necessary for the
adaptive interaction with the
environment
so
an interesting aspect is that the active
interference model was also applied to
interception which is termed
interceptive appearance
and it proposes that interceptive
experiences result from interferences
about the hidden causes of this sensory
information
so to put this
into the neural perspective
uh top-down interceptive predictions are
compared with bottom-up intercept
interceptive information most likely in
the insula
and the mismatch between both then
results in a prediction error
which is minimized depending on the
on the precision
by either perceptual inference or active
interference so
receptor inference means revising the
top-down interceptive predictions and
active impedance means then modifying
the bottom-up interceptive information
to convey with a prediction
and interestingly uh annual seth has
proposed that an emotion can also be
reviewed as interceptive influence
because interceptive prediction errors
are used to and fear emotional states
so to
connect this to physical and mental
health conditions um
deficits in interceptive processing for
example uh low interceptive accuracy
um might be associated with both
physical and mental health conditions
like chronic pain and comorbid
depression
um however there
is
um
it is not clear
how
that every disorder in every individual
might behave the same in this way i
think there are
differences so
um
so some disorders in individuals would
likely benefit from reducing overly
precise interceptive predictions
for example roaring beliefs about real
but indeed harmless sensations
while other patients might might reduce
overly precise and receptive information
which is
for example utilizary sensations that
are maintained that maintain roaring
beliefs so um there are both
possibilities
so let's talk about our approach on uh
how to influence to interceptive
information and this is osteopathy we
are all osteopaths uh the authors on
this paper
so a few words about osteopathy
osteopathy combines hands-on manual
approaches with
hands-off patient management approaches
so we use touch and manipulation as
hands-on which is informed of
sympathetic models of care so our
clinical reasoning
and hands-off patient-managed approaches
involve patient education psychological
support lifestyle advice but also
self-management solutions and these are
informed of course by osteopathic
principles
but notably both might utilize top-down
and bottom-up dynamics between
peripheral tissues and the brain
um
yes
so
in general osteopathy is applied to
treat a range of clinical conditions but
an emphasis is given on chronic pain
conditions in particular musculoskeletal
disorders like back pain
and
philosophically osteopathy has
emphasized the unity and interaction of
body mind and soul for
quite some time
and it has also been proposed that
it might benefit psychological outcomes
especially in chronic pain patients but
this needs some further research
and um
francesco and colleagues also proposed
that uh osteopathic treatment might
influence interceptive processing in a
concept paper they published in i think
and i went on to to conduct some primary
research showing that um
osteopathy indeed increases intraceptive
accuracy but also decreases uh the bulge
response of brain correlates of
interception in patients with chronic
low back pain
so
um they do so probably by the
stimulation of afferent c tactile fibers
which communicate interceptive and
effective dimensions of touch
so this could be relevant to both
physical and mental health conditions
that involve interceptive difficulties
which are for example chronic pain and
also depression
so this is our background and i think it
leads up to to the framework we like to
present
and the framework bridges all of these
fields of research and
it is an embodied interceptive but also
predictive framework
and
the basic basis is that both physical
and mental
health symptoms may result from altered
precision waiting between interceptive
predictions
and intercepted input so we argue that
literature argus that um either too much
precision is further to the prior which
is an overly precise prediction
on um or too little precision is
referred to the likelihood which is an
imprecise prediction error
so
arguably chronic pain and depression
are mainly linked to the overweighting
of priors
so um these beliefs likely predict
painful and depressive states even if
the actual interceptive information is
harmless
and they do so due to past experiences
and they likely make these states come
true through active interference
so the expected symptoms might be
generated through action to confirm the
prediction
and in order to update these prior
release and reduce the active influence
of pain and and depressed states
it is likely that surprising
interceptive input needs to be provided
and to increase first of all the weight
of the likelihood but also to generate
prediction errors that can revise the
belief
issuing the predictions and thus
osteopaths
likely need to foster perceptual
inference so actual information is used
in perceptual inference to update the
prediction and also the perception of
these symptoms
and we have a look at figure two in a
moment
so um
this uh there's a paper by far
from 2015 which which has argued that
contemplative practices may alter
interceptive processing by shifting
regulatory habits from active to
perceptual inference and i will we
believe that that osteopathy does the
same
so
if we have a look at our main figure
here um we propose that
we see a patient in red lying on the
treatment table
imagine this patient has um
chronic pain with comorbid depression
and he's lying there and the osteopath
provides some touch-based interventions
to the symptomatic area in this
this image the abdomen
and
we argue that
the belief or the prayer of the patient
is likely to predict physical and mental
states that are associated with pain and
depression because uh to be the likely
likely cause for uncertain information
and
this is the the overweighting of the
prior
but
if we provide some treatment
interventions to the patient
the sensory input
is not linked to these physically mental
states
which is surprising but osteopathic
treatment
often does not involve pain but is quite
pleasant if you if you touch a patient
so this is a surprising mismatch of
course to the patients to the patient
because the expected and the actual
information do not match
and
thus
generate an interceptive prediction
error
so these addiction errors need to be
minimized and they can be minimized
using active or perceptual inference and
in chronic pain we argue that
high precision is afforded to the belief
to the prior and low precision is
further to the sensory information and
the likelihood so the first process that
needs to be engaged is active
interference
um which likely produces the symptoms
uh that are resembling the predicted
states so
likely the autonomic nervous system is
engaged
to produce sensations that
resemble the expected
painful and depressive feeling
so uh however we are in a healthcare
context in osteopathic treatment so the
patient might also be declining uh
declined to
uh to think that this is a health
promoting intervention so um this is not
um
not uh
this is contradictory with the uh
with a prediction
so um it's active influence might not be
sufficiently to to
reduce and explain the interceptive
prediction errors so consequently we
argue that perceptual appearances
processes might be engaged
um to update then the belief and the
prior based on the likelihood so the
sensory information provided posted by
the osteopath might update the belief by
the patient
and thereby revising the generative
model holding the belief and issuing the
prediction
so
um we argue that these are the processes
that underpin osteopathic treatment um
in these kind of patients and especially
when an emotional reaction and treatment
develops
so um
yeah and in essence we argue that uh
belief and the prediction of physical
and mental
states that are associated with pain and
depression are updated
through
these interventions so the the
persistent and noisy interceptive
additions errors which maintain these
symptoms through active interference
might be replaced with surprising and
precise interceptive prediction errors
to alleviate the symptoms through
receptor computers
so this is
in a nutshell our framework
and we also of course need to discuss
this framework and have a look at some
implications also limitations
so in general i like to emphasize that
this theoretical framework is a
theoretical framework and therefore
requires experimental scrutiny for
verification or falsification so future
research
particularly needs to explore if
osteopathic treatment indeed
alleviates physical and mental symptoms
in this patient population also if it
actually increases interceptive accuracy
in this population
and likely also decreases allostatic
load and modulates autonomic nervous
system activity so there are a few
measurement tools we can use for that
and um other limitations
include
the
disregard of complexity both of the
health conditions but also of the
therapeutic approaches so osteopathy and
mental and depression and
chronic pain are all very complex
conditions and we have simplified them
like extremely so we overlooked
environmental factors
and we didn't
go into
explaining the patient therapist
relationship in detail as well but this
framework should be understood in this
context so it should be understood in a
person-centered context
and future studies might
also
have a look at
why manual treatment of peripheral
tissues sometimes leads to autonomic and
emotional
responses and i think this is the basic
of why i was so interested in this
research and these theories because in
practice that all frequently engaged
patients
which responded quite emotionally to
touch and um fake quite better after so
i wanted to to understand how this might
happen
so based on our hypothesis you can see
in figure
3 panel 8
that
the therapeutic input
that is
provided during treatment may contradict
the predicted state of pain and
depression
and produce an interceptive prediction
error
which is used to infer emotional states
and need to minimize minimize by active
influence harvest perceptive and what
you can see in nla is that the initial
active influence is quite
quick and sharp and we have seen or i've
seen
my colleagues as well from experience
that often if patients display emotional
responses during treatment
they firstly experienced some
sympathetic activity like sweating and
muscle tightness combined with emotional
distress for example
starting to cry
but these initial reactions
frequently
are replaced with
very
parasympathetic activity so the
breathing goes down and the patient
starts to relax and emotional calmness
starts to set in and i believe this is
quite well explainable with the
framework we have provided here because
an active interference might be the
first way to engage
in minimizing these prediction errors
and perceptive influence might be the
second and more sustainable way of
minimizing these predictions
so
lastly you can see on panel b
another
idea which might come from this
framework and this is the ground for
multidisciplinary collaborations in the
treatment of mental and physical
disorders
so we propose a kind of
integrative interceptive exposure
therapy in which
both physical but also mental health
specialists can come together and
work in a multi-disciplinary but also
person-centered care approach and the
idea is if you can see on the left-hand
side here is that
mindfulness practices
likely work top down uh helping the
patient to attend to the sensation that
he or she is experiencing
um but also
affecting the sensory information like
osteopathy working bottom up also
affecting the sensory information by
likely producing a sensation itself and
psychotherapy is slightly toward the top
down
to help identify and
also
reflect on the sensation and likely
works on
works on the prior the belief
directly and not through the sensory
information
so um these are a few few future
research ideas and now we can conclude
this presentation
and to put it all together
this hypothesis and theory article
proposes the embodied predictive and
interests of the framework
and it does so to reason and research
the effect of osteopathic treatment um
hesitatively on comodo psychological
factors in patients with persistent
physical conditions
and
one of the basic ideas is that
persistent physical and mental
conditions like chronic pain and
depression
may be underlined by first overly
precise interceptive predictions meaning
that
the symptom congruent information is
expected
and second imprecise interceptive
prediction errors meaning that
symptom incongruent information is not
sensed
so osteopathic treatment may provide
uncertain and surprising interceptive
information to the bodily area that is
associated with the physical and also
comorbid mental symptoms resulting in
interceptive prediction errors that
first engage active impedance processes
which lead to
initial autonomic activity resembling
the predicted symptoms
and this is
because it is the most likely cause of
uncertain interceptive information due
to the past experiences of the patient
and afterwards due to the contextual
factors uh the patient likely engages
perceptual appearance processes that
then update the maladaptive intercept
predictions based on
the actual interceptive information
and positivity might also
actually improve the ability to attend
to actual intercepted information
so in a nutshell persistent and noisy
interceptive prediction errors that
maintain the symptoms are likely
replaced with surprising and precise and
receptive prediction errors that
arguably alleviate the sentence
and in this way treatment might reduce
the belief about and also the prediction
of physical emitted states that are
associated with chronic pain and
comorbid depression
and we are currently also at the
osteopathic research institute
conducting research into
these approaches so thorson has also
joined us today um has developed
an approach to psychosomatic osteopathy
and we are currently having a look on
how these techniques might influence
stress levels and healthy participants
but also patients with chronic attention
type headaches so chronic
musculoskeletal disorders
so maybe there's
some things to follow in the future so
that's it thank you very much for your
attention i'm really looking forward to
the discussion and to engaging uh robert
george and francesco um
and here are the references i think i
scrolled through them shortly and if
someone's interested i think they can
get the presentation said right daniel
yes
so that's it
thanks lucas that was an awesome
presentation really a lot to
think and talk about
so
perhaps we'll first just open it up to
any of the authors and colleagues here
please just uh jump in wherever you'd
like i think
it'd be awesome to hear about just your
overview or what brought you to this
area of research as well as anything
that you picked up on from this last
presentation
i think maybe i can say a few words
because i forgot something in the
beginning so um it all started with with
george and francesco um inviting
inviting uh robert and me to join a
research group that um tries to to
reconceptualize osteopathic care under
the active endurance framework so
we have a group of osteopaths from
europe
working with the influence framework and
there are also other papers coming
in
a special topic which is also uh has
been
added by edited by george and francesco
so there's there are other ideas coming
forward in the near future
i think you know one one thing that um
i guess brought us into this area
you know it's a sort of a way of looking
into how we can best
help our patients in particularly those
with um you know present with complexity
um including you know chronic pain but
not just running by
uh you know the the broad sort of uh
area of persistent physical symptoms you
know those that
tend to sort of um go around see
different practitioners um
look for a solution to their problem try
to know what's going on
and you know we tend to sort of seat
them in practice and struggle at times
if we use um you know a very
reductionist approach to practice which
is do a manual intervention and hope for
the best you know that's that's far from
um you know from what is best practice
this day is what this patient-centered
care and also
can you still here i just lost george
for an audio i was just
gonna ask me too okay
i i can pick up a bit
um
[Music]
there's been a kind of a problem it with
osteopathic theory over the years um
which george is
uh hinting at around the reductionistic
the bio
[Music]
biomechanical model
and when it comes to complexity those
sorts of traditional ways of looking at
people's
chronic
symptoms
um leave something to be
um
well they they
they're not really
really things missing we we're realizing
using
uh if we draw from other disciplines
that we can see that there's a
potentially much better way to describe
why people
have these kind of chronic type symptoms
and um i i came into this a bit like
lucas with um
being quite surprised in practice about
how people reacted to treatment
and i think we have this um
it's almost a kind of a tacit uh sort of
thing within the profession that we we
treat people with emotional disturbance
but we don't actually
up front it
and so this conceptual framework is
actually starting to redress the balance
um which i think is really really
important and trying to understand why
is it people react
um i think the
this notion of prediction areas is um
kind of an interesting one
i i came into it a long time ago looking
at it from a psychodynamic point of view
and things called ab reactions
but i think what we're moving towards is
trying to come up with a bit more of a
unified theory and that's why i think
the
concepts of
active inference and activism are
actually starting to help
and also the participatory sense making
a movement also adds a lot to
how we can start to understand it
i know luke has mentioned we haven't
talked about the therapeutic
relationship but we are
there are other papers in the pipeline
that we'll look at
i'm losing my voice
i hope that sort of did a bit of a
summary for you george i mean
very interesting
george
no no no i i think robert you know did a
brilliant job in summarizing everything
so you know all the challenges and the
reasons why
you know we we are
interested in into exploring a different
kind of
way of
of looking at things
francesca or torsten would you like to
add anything um otherwise anyone in the
live chat is welcome to add a question
and i have some questions too
uh yes daniel so and one other um
viewpoint that i cannot at this point is
that from previous research that
actually we published looking at the
uh and using fmri but also other uh
neuroscience you know scientific tools
like for example thermocount
um we ended up understanding or
exploring the fact that actually the
brain is starting to react to specific
or general touch
in a kind of uh similar but different
way so and these actually creates a kind
of a question a research question on
where
the
ability of the specific manual therapies
approach
might intercede with a specific brain
bottom-up or top-down
uh in
an old-style way describing the how the
brain works because actually now we know
and looking in particular in the
inactivism that uh and an active
influence the body the brain actually
doesn't work without the with the top
down or bottom up and bottom outstream
so far but in a in a way we actually we
ended up saying that
probably uh the interaction with the
body so using a kind of uh affordance
and sense making so creating action
into the the uh
into the patient and
through the action of the uh the
therapeutic alliance and therefore
through the uh the uh professional and
the operator might create a kind of a
sharing
scenario or a sharing environment that
when with the
with the
concept of predictive processing and
active inference might also be explained
through the markov blankets
communication and markov blankets
connection between the
uh the the two the two elements uh so
the patient and the operator that some
something might happen
not only through the specific activity
that any type of manual therapist can do
but also in within a framework of
closeness between
the um
the the two uh the two elements indeed
one of the of the early study that also
lucas mentioned
what actually we did was just touching
the
uh the ankles of um and a healthy
patient lay down on the scan and we just
change our uh mental attitude on
focusing towards the hand or avoiding
the attention towards the hand so like
mimicking the way in which a
um a manual therapist was uh paying
attention to what he or she is doing
through
manual manual touch or
just being absolutely uh away from the
attention of the manuals and therefore
in the specific elements of the uh of
the of the research was just counting a
random bit
through the through the headphones so
and what actually we we saw is that in
in those people that were touched uh
through an attention towards the hand
there there was an higher activation of
the insula and the infra frontal gyrus
like in a way the the the perception of
the patient is
is before the fact that actually is
conscious of something happening from an
interceptive point of view within the
body so and the body is saying do you
know what i'm feeling something that
actually i'm processing through an
interceptive framework in the in the
insula and at the same time i'm changing
my
um
endos endogenous or exogenous attention
based on the way in which you touch me
so and therefore this creates a more
complex environment in which actually we
we we would like to understand better
and we think that and the inactive
uh approach is one of the and with all
its
let's say subsections and elements that
might be an inter interesting way of
interpreting or at least trying to read
what it's happening in the complex
clinical environment
thank you
so
i'll make an observation and then ask a
question so robert i really like what
you said about uh being motivated
from earlier on by what you saw the
outcomes of treatment were and then that
was kind of alluded to in what we just
heard
like um you could be touching someone's
ankle
but it's not just the ankle that might
change maybe it's their knee but maybe
it's something in their head but then
maybe it's something in their
organ or their brain or their mind
and um
that idea of like entering at the
anomaly
is it's very clinical like i'm not that
kind of a doctor but that's kind of what
i understand to be done like looking for
patterns and anomalies
and then it's also
very at home in the realm of
participatory sense making like you also
address but also that's kind of active
inference which is relative to a
generative model of the world
observations are either consistent or
surprising in some way
and so that was just kind of it's an
interesting tie-in and i think it just
speaks to how
even in a qualitative or just a
conceptual
level
across different domains we can like
talk about active inference as well as
other areas and there are concordances
and it's not like one has to nest over
the other there are different domains
and um approaches
so um robert any thoughts on that or i
have other questions
yeah i think um
there needs to be some
some kind of a dressing of
um
you got to you know you have
a relationship between a practitioner
and the patient
and i think the participatory sense
making
can start to
somehow dissolve a little bit of the the
kind of normative language
which
has become problematic so so anomalies
in the past have been
dismissed as in oh you're not getting
better because you're not
reacting to the treatment properly
whereas these types of approaches are
saying oh oh
there is a shared
narrative and i think the narrative
medicine movement is also quite
important in in these ideas obviously we
can't write about that as well
um
but it's it's it's nice i think you've
picked up on that sort of
multi-dimensional and
crossover between different disciplines
because i think that's another thing
we're trying to make a big point of in
this paper
we need to reach out to other
disciplines and say look
we have this way of doing things but we
know we're not we don't have the whole
picture at all
but if we can combine
um
with
psychologists psychiatrists
i mean all of all of us on the paper
we've all gone outside of osteopathy to
to look at other disciplines
um
and again that's the kind of another
kind of it's like a meta kind of
participatory sense-making that goes
into
i think what we're trying to achieve
like someone will look at that figure
and you all are saying hey we're the
person above the table with the hands on
and with medical training
but then there's another part that you
didn't go into detail on what would be
that
therapy component or the
niche modification component so totally
agree that the paper is like an
invitation and that was really um to my
question
like we see in other domains and
applications of active inference you
reframe something that might have been
perceived about like um
just
reward
or
a normative
precision based approach like this is
the reference range this you're getting
your objective function is to enter that
reference range and it's like a red flag
if it's not
um towards this more
perhaps even customized uh
reduction of
uncertainty um
and the body like predicting its own
sensation so i just wondered what are
the implications
does that
play a role in how the medical expert
understands the scenario does it play a
role in
the patient's own understanding of
what's happening just
how
beyond the research predictions and
experiments that are being described how
does this translate into a um
clinical experience
so one of the things uh it's quite
interesting you bringing the you know
the concept of nature construction um on
the other paper that we have in the
pipeline where we explore we actually
argue that australia osteopathic care is
a kind of a effective inference
uh
you know an argument around you know the
construction of you know a niche which
can be a diet uh in the case in most
adult interactions in clinical practice
but you can also go beyond that and be
it with a triadic kind of relationship
for example
when you're treating a baby where
actually
it's not a two-way communication between
the practitioner and the baby but it's
also with with the parents
with the mother and and in fact you know
the first person you need to bring you
need to synchronize is probably with the
mother as well because you know if you
if you kind of treat the baby indirectly
you get there so i think that there's a
lot of sort of alignments a lot of
synchrony um to take into account into
the therapeutic encounter
and you know arguably the the kind of
the development of a robust uh throbbing
alliance is through that when the two
people sort of sharing uh sharing a
common niche but also sharing a you know
common kind of uh you know mental states
and predicting
uh in a lot of times without any words
uh what the response of the other person
is is likely to be so it could be uh for
some people may sort of sound a little
bit uh
more kind of esoteric but if we put it
through a lens of you know active
inference in activism and so on sense
making
you talking about things that are
pre-reflective
you're talking about things that's just
happened
and
when um
even down the realms of at times we hear
practitioners or our own experiences
practitioners on kind of bodily work
then you feel like at times that uh you
know the patient is seems to be relaxing
because you got some relaxation through
your own kind of a body and it's a sort
of
it could be the esoteric side of things
but also you could think that maybe that
show that demonstrates some form of
alignment maybe that demonstrates an
element of synchrony
that can be done at such a more
physiological level so
there's a lot of um you know there's a
lot of mileage
uh in in my opinion and in exploring
clinical practice uh particularly in
particular in in situations of with an
element of
of complexity to explore it through them
you know these lenses
yeah and also yes
yeah and also uh these also in line with
the um the most recent theoretical paper
just published a few a few months ago by
um
antonio damasio and
and
colleagues
uh where actually they they were looking
at the
complexity through the um
the
interceptive nervous system so what
actually they called for the first time
ever no
intercepted nervous system so it's a
system that includes not only the fact
that actually
we need to understand what it's going in
um within our body so the old concept
between what's the old concept of crane
so how do you feel
but it's also goes into the the fact
that the body actually interacts with
the environment and also the uh that
beautiful issue on
uh neuro or neuroscience uh based on uh
interception where actually they try to
predict you uh say
something new in in terms of uh
interception where
the uh the the main hypothesis was that
the the way in which we create
interception that is
the base for a complex clinical
condition
is not only related to the fact that the
different brain areas and therefore the
introspective
nervous system it's creating a kind of
interaction between all the autonomic
and non-autonomic uh areas but also
those areas are important for um for
decoding what it's happening outside the
body and therefore through a sun through
a descending
primary and secondary descending
mechanism that actually they're in
introduce new variables within uh within
the system that uh it allows the system
to detect and to understand better the
complexity and through this complexity
created the
appropriate changes that might be helped
and for um keeping the non-equilibrium
city state and therefore all the concept
in relation to the predicted cause
so what is the how we we can intercede
with that because actually we are using
one element that is touch that in a way
might be disturbing the system because
actually it's using
in particular gentle touch or what is
called affective touch is disturbing or
interacting with the system and just
through those uh anatomy functional
pathways that actually goes directly to
the insula and so through the ct fibers
and therefore we are interacting uh in
an ascending way uh with that specific
areas that are including the um
interceptive nervous system that
actually actually are they the one on
the part for emerging the uh the
elements that we are talking about now
and why it's important as just to
underline what joe said which uh
i found very clever and i support that
so it's a way of creating a sort of uh
entry point that
also in the complex system might
intercede with something that is
multi-factorial within the well within
the body that not only includes for
example
pain the perception of pain and the
experience of pain and all the elements
that are
inside the body but also it creates the
the bound with something that is
external and bonding with external it
means that actually you are establishing
the therapeutic alliance in terms of the
dyadic but also indirectly the triadic
condition when actually you treat for
example a baby or an early person so
when actually there is someone there
might be a parent there might be a
the son the daughter or legal guardian
actually are bringing the uh that person
into you into the clinical encounter and
therefore are part of the uh the general
uh treatment uh session so i think it's
a it's a way by by looking at the
neuroscience behind that and the
theoretical theoretical framework and
the practical examples that are
clinically
found can be clinically found it can can
be clinically explored i think there is
a nice way also to
um uh intercede with the uh with a
different lens uh to understand complex
situations
i would add something to
yes please torsten
okay i would add something to um what
was said by jay telly and basharsh
and
was that
i would even go a step further
i mean we decided to support
luka's work financially because it is
part of the psychosomatic asparty and
our point of view but it's not only
that we want to interact our palpation
in reaction to interception but also to
body sensations to arousals to emotions
to belief systems and from my point of
view in this case the osteopath is less
a therapist but more a co-regulator by
the interaction between both of them the
awareness of the patient to his own
stimulus in different levels will
increase and secondly
from the beginning osteopathy was
interested in interrelationships
and this means that we are already in
our own profession in a way
interdisciplinary so it means for
example that also we could look that
peripheral hyperglycamine will lead
always to a central hypoglycemia
to
central uh
glucopini even so it means you have no
more sugar in your brain so even if you
would touch and you do all your
psychological stuff but by your
metabolic system you create a
hypoglycemia in your brain even then
whatever you do it will not has a big
result so as more
fragmented areas in the functioning of
the patient's health we can include in
our treatment and this means basically
which was in the past not so much
dominant and more active patient
because in research it was show
proactivity is one of the most factors
to be healthy and basically in an
australian treatment the patient is
laying passively most of the time in the
past so here we have not only looking in
research how osmatic treatment can help
but even change ospatic treatment in a
more
post-modern way
so where we can help the patient even
more with our hands instead
what was past treatments done in
australic treatment before
so actually on that theme of kind of
origins and futures of osteopathy i'll
read a comment from the live chat and
anyone else can write a chat too
um
good morning my dear osteopathic
brothers and sisters i'm an american
osteopath and must leave for work now
but wanted to share a history of the
still hildreth hospital in kirksville
which was an outgrowth of dr stills
original concept wishing to have
osteopathic applications to mental
health
there are still papers papers by still
which came out of that institution about
effects osteopathy had on mental health
conditions and early research on
osteopathy and mental health from mel
friedman who
is actually my father so um any thoughts
on that and
also just keeping in mind the guest
stream is kind of a two-way street
people inactive inference who are
perhaps hearing about osteopathy for the
first time and vice versa just what
are some of those
principles lucas that you mentioned in
your presentation informed by
osteopathic principles like what are
some of those principles
and origins and how has it changed
because it was very interesting what
torsten had addressed
yeah so i think an important distinction
that we have to make is between american
osteopaths and osteopaths mostly around
the world because um i for myself i'm
not a medical doctor so in
the us
um
the old the do is a medical doctor in
osteopathic uh in the osteopathic field
so they are um they can treat mental
health conditions and psychiatric
disorders and it is regulated that they
can do this so in germany for example i
can't treat someone with a major
depression because my training was not
oriented to allow me to treat that so it
is important for us to
to emphasize that we are um not treating
mental disorders on our own but that we
try to um
address
psychological factors in people with
physical conditions that are visiting us
quite frequently so i think that that is
another distinction that i have to make
between our colleagues from america
and then to the point of of the history
of osteopathy we came across a few
papers um that have argued for an
osteopathic psychiatry i think that was
involved in this paper a little bit in
the earlier times
and um
there has been some work done but the
work is as your father has outlined
quite old so uh we we try to put some
new perspectives uh to this discussion i
think
that
it's another thing
one thing if i may uh would be
useful to to add is
you know the origins of australia with
undertale still and and some of you know
his early
students including um john martin little
john
were uh were primarily based around you
know new concepts um you know concepts
of you know
sort of
uh unity self-regulation that were kind
of uh
relatively new in the late 19th century
and and a lot of the work was sort of
one one interesting and important
concept of the concept of adaptation so
you know enabling people to adapt to
uh to their day-to-day activities to to
adapt and interact with the environment
unfortunately that was a little bit loss
uh lost over the years and
endoscopity and other forms of manual
therapy chiropractic for
musculoskeletal physiotherapy became a
long time
based on a kind of very biomechanical
model of care you know looking primarily
at the test structure the
musculoskeletal structures the reason
for uh quite quite a lot of the of the
clinical problems which
you know in fact led to um hoover and
american australian 1963 to to write a
very important paper that not many
people actually read
or actually acted on which actually
called for osteopathy or osteopathic
medicine to be ecological medicine
because you know it's not about just the
theology it's not about sort of using a
pure biomechanical biomedical model and
try to find
what is the cause of the problem what is
the pathology so i think you know the
interesting thing over the years and
actually that's um you know something
that actually
um
you know personally attracted me a lot
to this and to these new ideas uh is
actually these ideas
uh kind of are are very much you know in
in a sense
aligned with those initial ideas of lost
geography where everything kind of
started from concept of this sort of
adaptation as a central concept around
the free energy principle for example
the interactions with the environment
central consciousness concepts around
inactivism so really to think about the
person in that sort of unique ecological
niche and how can we as practitioners
kind of help that person to you know
help with self-regulation etc also
taking into account the knowledge we
have these days about what is actually
the role of the nervous system pretty
much about you know in the role of our
stages for example
uh not so much about some sort of the
high order cognitive stuff so i think
there's
there's a lot to extract from
you know these frameworks and and not
necessarily try to rewrite the history
of osteopathy or other forms of
nanotherapy but actually
applying things in a in a kind of a
critical
and you know serious manner to actually
sort of move forward and move away from
uh
you know from sort of you know ideas
that actually no longer make that much
sense from for example you know
practicing entirely on a biomechanical
model of of you know of care
i like very much what george was saying
and basically it was not only whoever it
was already little john and mcconnell
who gone in this way what hoover
explored more and we are on the way of
them basically so if we nowadays look
also into genetics which was in the
beginning of osteopathy not possible
look into epigenetics look into un
lifestyle factors and with each factor
the success ability of a person to get
sick or get health increases
and if we include this with our patient
we are on the way
of
little john mcconnell and who was opened
up for us already in the very early
times of osteopathy
thank you torsten robert and then anyone
else
yeah i just
don't want to lose sight of the fact
that the paper is about
recognizing that even though we might
not be trained to
deal with psychological interventions an
awful lot of our patients have
psychological
problems of some order or another i
think
something like 40
of primary care consultations coexist
with mental disturbance
so whether we like it or not we're
dealing with it
and this is a this is a way we can go
we're not training people we're not
saying osteopaths should become psycho
psychotherapists or psychologists but
we're saying
if we
raise awareness of these issues
is going to help in our patient care
i agree very much what robot was saying
and even i would go a step further we
can't avoid to interchange with
emotional being with
the ans being with cognitive levels of a
person we only can be a little bit more
competent when we treat with our patient
in these areas and this doesn't mean
that we need to be a psychotherapist in
treating patients
it's the complex systems perspective
that the entity is in the niche and that
the mind and body are
interrelated inseparable and so
any model that for some sort of like um
credentialing reason chooses to ignore
that is going to be operating in peril
so how do we
recognize this system's complexity but
also the amend
immense amount of information you know
you could study just the liver and there
would be a lot to learn or just the
lungs so how do we pull back and
actually have a healthy
relationship in this very complex
setting
so here's a sort of um fun question also
staying with the anomaly theme
i was wondering if throughout your
training or experiences had come across
any embodied
exercises that you think are really good
entry points to
the predictive body and interoception so
like i was thinking of having one's arms
in the door frame and trying to raise
them out
and then when you step out you know the
arms will raise
and um i was wondering if there was any
other
experiences that might be that anomaly
for someone to start wondering if they
were
interested to look into more of these
approaches that you outline in the paper
rather than
the signal processing perception
framework or some other um
non or pre-act imp model
so i i think the literature is quite
dense with examples on on how the the
body influences the mind in these kind
of instances
um for example going back to to struck
who published the study with the pen in
between the teeth uh showing that people
find comics much more funnier if they
had a pen between the teeth because this
pen activates the supermarket major with
this the primary muscle of laughing so
there are quite a few examples on
how simple manipulations of the body
framework influences
cognition and emotion
but i don't have some specific uh
exercises uh to to give to patients um
if that answers the question
right because also daniel i think it
depends from the patient's condition so
far so if we take into account what we
what we said up to now so it means that
uh each pain each patient has got its uh
his or her own
clinical specific condition so and uh
going into a protocol lies for example
exercise my ended up with patients
having different reactions
so and therefore the the use of
this framework that consider the
complexity of the patient
within
the uniqueness of uh
of shame or hair
definitely my uh help us to be
to have fantasy or to have imagination
during the during the during the
the treatment and adapt
the different possibilities
that might be exercising might be uh
treatment procedures it might be
techniques and might be approaches
into the condition of the patient that
is not only the patient but is the the
patient within the environment within
his or her environment and therefore
create the optimal way of what we
predict that might be optimal for uh for
the patient in order to achieve the uh
the outcome that was um
that needs to be obtained obtained
i think there's uh
in fact you know i'm just thinking one
exercise that i
tend to use and it's nothing that
i develop myself but it's used by quite
a number of practitioners to
you know so
to teach patients about pain and and
about the sensations they feel is for
example to use the analogy to do
you know the
sort of
this so you if you ask a patient if for
example in cases of patients with
chronic pain fear of movement you
identified that for example movement
tends to be quite slow and and
and certainly restricted not so much
because there's a serious limitation in
the movement but because there's a fear
of movement they tend to use for example
as the professional looking if you make
a fist and you try to move your wrist
it's going to feel uncomfortable and
that's in a sense how
how your neck is trying to move against
you resisting if you try to move relax
you know it's the sensations are
completely different so you can actually
create if you think about these
exercises that are used by
you know quite a lot of musculoskeletal
practitioners to actually start
introducing the the sort of some
some of the the sensations that we want
uh that might actually violate their
generative model and change things a
little bit so that's a good way of you
know try to teach the patients you know
this is how you should feel this is how
you should move and not so much like
trying to move against resistance which
happens if you make a fist and try to
you know move your wrist
in general i like well it's very much
also francesco's
commentary because in osteopathy we try
really to identify
uh individualized approaches so there
was a nice research from amy cutty where
she changed body postures and measured
the cortisol and testosterone outcomes
but in
research it was not confirmed because it
was too
it was not adapted to a certain person
sometimes it's enough that just a slight
extension in two verticals can give a
person a different
kind of breathing experience in another
person it could be that just
the face could be a little bit released
in some muscles like for example
lucas was mentioned so i think the
approaches to a patient in an ospatic
treatment is very individualized
and it's not a general
techniques for everybody which
could help
so good as in individualized approaches
in relation to different experiences
thanks for all the
awesome and diverse answers so i'll
ask the question um
carefully i guess but standardized
interventions whether they're measured
in milligrams or
educational curriculum
lend themselves towards being
scientifically tested more easily like a
two group experiment people who do or
don't have the diagnosis
or
any other number of situations and it
was really also just highlighted in what
torsten added with this
uh
individuated experience and the dyad is
unique there's never going to be another
one like that in the history of
osteopathy with those people in that
niche interacting that way
so
just wondered um what insights from all
of your different areas of expertise
start to
help us
address like the specificity of the
particulars of an encounter but also
know what
kinds of things should be available
for population level use or on average
you know are eggs good or bad
yeah i think this is a really big
problem in osteopathy um and research
osteopathic research in general is what
kind of control groups are we are we
doing so if we if we are treating a
patient is a
mere touch without intention a good
control group or no intervention so
there are many problems to the
to researching the person-centered
nature of osteopathy but also the manual
nature of osteopathy and i think
francesco is a good person to speak
about this because he recently published
a paper on control
interventions in osteopathy maybe you
want to add something francesca
um
thanks lucas so uh i think the
this is a very interesting um
question uh daniel um for three reasons
so the first one is that
we are
still within um a drug based research
paradigm
because actually um during the la from
1980 some word the and then with the
development of evidence-based medicine
the majority of the research actually
was drug-based research and therefore we
can control milligrams as you said we
can control the the type of
administration and all the elements that
actually created the randomized control
trial very controlled very specific and
so on
however uh in during the last 10 years
uh all these paradigms actually start to
like having some creepy things
and in which sense because actually uh
it's
it's very far away from the from the
clinical practice
and the clinical practice is based on
variability
and the variable and our clients and the
variability in our clients are important
to understand what are the clinical
effects
of a specific treatment
so um indeed
during the last 15 years this concept of
having
super rigid
randomized control trial in particular
in the intervention group and therefore
in the control group actually started to
change the sun to be molded in a way
of creating
something it's much more
much closer to the reality therefore
they ended up with pro pragmatic
clinical trial and
pragmatic clinical trial those trials
actually are more
are closer to the reality in which there
is not just one an administration in
terms of for example drug treatment but
actually they are taking into account
all the different elements that might
influence the effect of the treatment
itself indeed when actually we
administer for example
a drug
but then
we looking for long-term
effects on long-term outcomes in the
intervention group an intervention group
then goes back home and they are one
group one part of this intervention
group is very very happy because they
just
they just got in a new child uh they
just had and they just won the lottery
and all the positive elements obviously
the long-term effects of the the drug
treatment is definitely better than
the uh the someone instead who
for example had lost
so what is the the what is the concept
underneath that is the concept of the
the research is changing and also the
methodological elements underneath
research are changing now there are
pragmatic trials but they're also what
they call the benchmarking control trial
so there are actually are trials that
are important
for detecting what is happening during
the clinical
routine life within the hospital and
then adding another intervention to the
normal routine care then you see what is
the difference between the two pathways
so what it's saying by that it's saying
that it is true that it's important to
control all the variables
within a given intervention but at the
same time
if we look at the cause effect and
therefore efficacy yes it's important if
we want to look at what is in
instead it's called effectiveness so the
clinical effect of the specific
treatment then what you do what you
specifically do a specific treatment or
uh 10 grams 10 grams more or 15 grams
left
actually doesn't make so
that difference because of the what we
are talking here and also because
probably those 15 grams are
less are and probably
will have more powerful effects if i'm
talking to the patient with the right
tone
and therefore creating an inducing
and increased effect
uh based on the
uh interaction the narrative the shared
narratives that we are talking so in a
way it's true but at the same time uh
the the recent evidence are shifting the
uh the methodological research com
concept towards complex intervention
thanks for the awesome response and
indeed it is mirroring
trends in other scientific areas to
study
um targeted perturbations and measuring
dynamical systems after perturbation or
testing different dynamical models
rather than just summary statistic and
t-test and then you know rubber-stamped
that so it is absolutely
really um interesting um
does anyone else have any uh comments or
questions or things here please robert i
mean there's quite a tradition in the
nursing world to look at action research
which is real life in real life
interventions you know what happens at
the ground level and i think that's
really where we are
that's what we're saying
you know what actually happens in the
treatment room not what we think what
happens but actually what happens
and this is a conceptual framework that
enables that
so almost within active it'd be like the
difference between what we think is
going to happen like well if
the two comparisons of the two different
amounts had this effect on the biomarker
well then the one that had the better
biomarker effect should be used in the
clinic right
and so that's like staying within the
generative model but then
always being open to having new
information and being able to have um
discernment to know whether it's
consistent or inconsistent with our
expectations but our expectations for
complex systems even people we know very
well like they can still
surprise you and so
um but always keeping that openness to
the
even the tactile which is something that
a lot of other medical modalities don't
do
so maybe the tactile five percent of the
time it diverts
a cohort of patients towards another
diagnosis like the tissue is warm
but that at the whole population level
wouldn't even be statistically
significant
but it might be very important for a
small subset so it's very interesting
about like kind of
pointing without um
dwelling on some of the limitations
of the current
medical system which i think most people
can agree
is uh not realizing our preferences
and then here's actually a
science-informed way
when we can start to look at
complex interventions
in human systems
absolutely and
therefore there there are still they are
starting we are starting to have also
some theories
uh behind that
uh that can be um a complexity or living
system that actually can be also applied
into uh this field um
this changing
view of the research field that up to
now as we said was mainly based on
was biased towards the former
pharmaceutical
standpoint
any other
thoughts or comments on that
yeah this is a very big point francesco
is saying and all his uh his extremely
engagement in
in helping us to get more science is
incredibly important
basically to have a little bit balanced
we will never have a full balance
because with our treatment we can't make
so much money like farmer concern can do
but at least uh we have opportunities
for
uh opening uh doors in
in a way that is
closer to reality
and creating
um
a a way that up to now
is the mainstream because actually also
the um uh drug based uh treatment
actually are uh facing uh big challenges
up to now
and the more you go either you go in
ultra precise medicine
because actually we are all going all
the way down and deep into
precise medicine or you need to go on
the opposite side in the middle
everything is already discovered
so uh therefore there are chances to
integrate the two because there are
chances because actually we are living
in a way that actually we need precise
medicine
uh but at the same time we need also um
complex intervention we need complex way
of looking
at the
uh in a different way not in a
super segmented way
uh but in a way that actually it brings
everything together
i think another
piece the puzzle was brought up when
someone mentioned the early paper about
osteopathic approaches as ecological
medicine because in my own research with
insect ecology that was always the
question well you could have the insects
in the lab and then you know what age
they were and what they ate but then
the temperature and the humidity aren't
what they have evolved to experience and
you don't know whether they're healthy
but then out in the wild they're doing
interesting stuff in the way that it's
meant to happen but you don't know how
old the animal is or you don't know what
its physiological condition is or you
don't get the measurements and so
there's a dialogue there between the
more controlled laboratory side
which is like kind of precision medicine
i mean some people may want to live in a
laboratory if that means that they could
make more measurements about their body
and then there's sort of the field
ecology
natural history
angle
so
that's very um interesting how there's
like a medical
along with a mental health
and ecological synthesis happening in a
sense
through osteopathy
that
now a lot of different perspectives are
helping to combine
um
typified and lucas's very dense and
informative slides
is one of the ease we mentioned
yes
there are many e's
and like maybe the term inactive might
not come in also
it's another heat okay
seven e
more used um but
it also shows how different um
ways of describing across fields can
prevent their synthesis like again
osteopathy might not have used the term
inactivism
but
i mean looking back on it isn't it it's
almost
it's it's not even to say it's
definitional it's like an understatement
so then there's a lot of latent
possibility and then how does that get
applied and how does it um
change the way that the
art and the science are carried out are
enacted themselves
um
if anyone else would like to ask a
question or like
what would you say to those who are
learning active inference and
just hearing about what you've described
for the first time or those maybe from
the medical or osteopathic community who
are learning about active inference for
the first time in sort of closing
i would say that
active inference
provides um
a way
in which we can actually simplify
things you know rather than making them
more complex i think there's a lot to
you know people would feel scared
there's another model and there's
another kind of complex thing to look
into it in fact if you look at sort of
the basic foundations of active
inference
is actually things make perfect sense
and in fact
you can simplify uh
your interaction with your patients in
and become a much more effective lawyer
you know the kind of uh
you know when you get to that point
where you know that things are working
well
since you know your internal states are
my
active states and and vice versa when i
can predict
things
so um
i think you can can
can help us with that can also help us
to um to understand
you know complexity that patients bring
to the table
and you know the paper is about mental
health and oxyoptine you know a lot of
people would argue post job is primarily
based on
focused on musculoskeletal care but as
we've been talking about
you know most musculoskeletal care and
the most musculoskeletal conditions have
an element of mental health
in a sense the patient that
can't get out don't do their normal
day-to-day activities when their world
stops making sense is likely to become
depressed so if you
by working on their you know
musculoskeletal problems make them feel
better
indirectly or even directly you are
treating their mental health conditions
so
i think
can help us to see the bigger picture
rather than simply the dysfunction in
the body
for the brain in fact
i definitely echo that
with george and i think what i've
learned and i've been working in this
field for 30 years
is this is giving us a handle on some of
the uncertainty that goes on
as a practitioner
a lot of my students get really scared
about how to deal with unpredictable
things that occur in practice
and it can be you know pretty
challenging because there's a lot of
complexity
and i think the big take-home message
i'd say is you don't have to be the
expert on your patient
this gives us
a handle
yeah i mean you have a hard enough time
to be an expert on yourself
but to be an expert with another human
being is
pretty damn difficult
this gives us a model framework
it's some way it's reinventing things
that may other people have said in the
past but it's it's starting to bring it
all together into a package that says
right
there's a
ecological niche or you could say a
shared narrative there's a way of
talking to a patient
that you don't have to tell them what to
do that we can kind of work out
we can facilitate
healing and that actually
is what initially got me into osteopathy
i think this is a very interesting point
robert
and i
it resonates with a
thing that is
an osteopathic principle that we try to
activate the self-healing powers of
patients and
this implies for me that we are not
the therapist who brings up healing in
the patient but the patient in itself is
generating the healing and therefore we
are not the specialists who have to
understand the complexity of the patient
but to be there as a as a counterpart
and evolve with the patient to generate
a more healthy life
i can't help but remark on robert what
you said there about not having to be an
expert
it reminded me of how like the arm
doesn't have to be a theoretical coffee
cup
subject matter expert
it has to implement a strategy of which
a broad range are going to be possible
and none of them can be pre-stated but
it has to implement a strategy
to get the coffee cup
and so
it's just a very
um
interesting way to tie together the
trans-disciplinarity
with also one of the
threads of inactivism and ecological
psychology and active inference which is
that we're doing
and thinking and doing are together
rather than waiting to be
subject matters on experts on everything
before we
are able to act in a complex niche that
includes us as a part but we're not
going to get the whole picture on
well this was a very
fun discussion it sounds like you all
are on a very
cool line of research and we
really appreciate it in the lab i hope
that you'll come back and discuss more
as
more research occurs
thank you thank you daniel thank you
very much all right thanks a lot okay
have a good day thanks everyone
youtube okay bye-bye see you soon